Guide to the Women's Department of Health and Physical Education Records, 1923 - 1976 UA.25.05.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Alphabetical Files, 1923-1976
  - Facilities
    - Correspondence re ECAC
      - With architects, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 186)
      - With Development Office, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 187)
      - With Donors, 1953, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 188)
      - With majors and former staff, May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 189)
      - With students and staff, July 1976-January 1979 (Box 3, Folder 190)
    - Fund-raising
      - Cost Break-down, circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 191)
      - Gift Record, 1972-1980 (Box 3, Folder 192)
      - SPUD, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 193)
      - Student Projects, Fall 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 194)
      - Swim-a-Thon, April 1976 (Box 3, Folder 195)
    - Peavey's Letter to Donors concerning use of money for renovation, January 30, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 196)
    - Donors' Response to Renovation of Memorial Gym instead of ECAC, January 1981-February 1981 (Box 3, Folder 197)
    - Renovation vs. New Construction - Architect's estimate, February 1981 (Box 3, Folder 198)
    - Renovation vs. New Construction (Contrast of Resulting Usefulness), 1981 (Box 3, Folder 199)
  - History
    - Talk by Julia R. Grout to the Dean's Staff, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 200)
    - Letter from Julia R. Grout to Dean Wannamaker, September 21, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 201)
    - Clippings, 1954-1966 (Box 3, Folder 202)
    - Development of P. E. for Women at Duke University, by Julia R. Grout (Box 3, Folder 203)
    - All About Duke Physical Education Majors, 1945-1976, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 204)
  - Photographs
    - Anatomy (Box 3, Folder 205)
    - Archery (Box 3, Folder 206)
    - Badminton (Box 3, Folder 207)
    - Basketball (Box 3, Folder 208)
    - Bowling (Box 3, Folder 209)
    - Diving (Box 3, Folder 210)
    - Fencing (Box 3, Folder 211)
    - Field Hockey (Box 3, Folder 212)
    - First Aid (Box 3, Folder 213)
    - Golf (Box 3, Folder 214)
    - Gymnastics, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 215)
    - Gymnastics, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 216)
    - Gymnastics and Stunts, circa 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 217)
    - Major Students and their Families (Box 3, Folder 218)
    - Modern Dance
      - circa 1939-1950 (Box 3, Folder 219)
      - circa 1940-1950 (Box 3, Folder 220-222)
      - circa 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 223)
      - circa 1948-1953 (Box 3, Folder 224)
      - circa 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 225)
      - circa 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 226)
    - Nereidians (Box 3, Folder 227-228)
    - Riding (Box 3, Folder 229)
    - Skating (Box 3, Folder 230)
    - Softball (Box 3, Folder 231)
    - Square Dance (Box 4, Folder 232)
    - Staff (Box 4, Folder 233-234)
    - Staff members and their families (Box 4, Folder 235)
    - Swimming (Box 4, Folder 236)
    - Tennis (Box 4, Folder 237)
    - Track and Field (Box 4, Folder 238)
    - Used in P.E. Brochure (Box 4, Folder 239)
    - Volleyball (Box 4, Folder 240)
    - WAA (Box 4, Folder 241)
    - War Time Activity (Box 4, Folder 242)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 243)
  - Publicity
    - Alumni Register, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 244)
    - Clippings, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 245)
    - Clippings, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 246)
    - Clippings, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 247)
    - Modern Dance, circa 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 248)
    - Modern Dance, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 249)
    - Modern Dance, undated (Box 4, Folder 250)
    - Nereidians, circa 1956-1968 (Box 4, Folder 251)
    - P.E. Major Brochures, circa 1950-1974 (Box 4, Folder 252)
    - Staff News, circa 1958-1971 (Box 4, Folder 253)
  - Recreation
    - Women's Athletic Association
      - List of WAA Presidents and Vice Presidents, 1930-1959 (Box 4, Folder 254)
      - WAA Cabin, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 255)
      - WAA Handbooks, 1944-1959 (Box 4, Folder 256)
      - Minutes of WAA Board, 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 257)
      - Constitution of WAA, 1946, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 258)
      - Delta Phi Rho Alpha, circa 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 259)
      - Special Meeting of staff regarding Intramural Program, January 18, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 260)
    - Women's Recreation Association
      - Handbooks, 1959-1970 (Box 4, Folder 261)
      - List of WRA Presidents and Vice Presidents, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 262)
      - Constitution of WRA and Program, 1961-1972 (Box 4, Folder 263)
      - Picture of 1962-1963 WRA Board (Box 4, Folder 264)
      - History of WAA and WRA written by Nancy Ingram, WRA President, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 265)
      - Activities of WRA, 1964-1971 (Box 4, Folder 266)
    - East Campus Recreation
      - Women's Intramurals, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 267)
      - Photos of Intramurals, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 268)
      - Big 4 Sports Days, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 269)
      - Co-Rec, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 270)
      - Recreation Summary
        - 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 271)
        - 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 272)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 273)
        - 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 274)
      - Handbooks and Brochures, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 275)
      - Schedule of Recreation Activities, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 276)
    - Performance Groups
      - Modern Dance, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 277)
      - Modern Dance, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 278)
      - Modern Dance, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 279)
      - Nereidians, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 280)
  - Staff Meetings
    - 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 281)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 282)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 283)
    - 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 284)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 285)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 286)
    - 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 287)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 288)
  - Task Force and Curriculum Committee Action
    - Professional Views on Required P. E., circa 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 289)
    - Professional Views on Recreation, circa 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 290)
    - AMA Position on P. E., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 291)
    - Student Views on P. E., 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 292)
    - Women's Athletics at Duke, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 293)
    - Administrative Structure of P. E. in Other Schools, circa 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 294)
    - Action regarding P.E., Spring 1973 (Box 4, Folder 295)
    - Men's P.E. Dept. Information, circa 1973 (Box 4, Folder 296)
    - Professional Views on the Administration of P. E., 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 297)
    - Recreation at Duke, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 298)
    - Future Directions - Men's and Women's P.E. to Task Force, April 1974 (Box 4, Folder 299)
    - Report to the Curriculum Committee on P.E. Requirement, April 1974 (Box 4, Folder 300)
    - Interim Statement of Task Force, May 1, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 301)
    - Reaction of Men's and Women's P.E. Depts. To the Task Force, May 1974 (Box 4, Folder 302)
    - Description of Women's Dept., Spring 1974 (Box 4, Folder 303)
    - Student Reaction to Interim Report of the Task Force, June 10, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 304)
    - Correspondence between Partin and Evans regarding Task Force position, June 1974 (Box 4, Folder 305)
    - Meeting of Task Force, October 30, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 306)
    - Report of Task Force, November 1974 (Box 4, Folder 307)
    - Response of Men's and Women's Depts. to Task Force Report of November 1974 (Box 4, Folder 308)
    - Change and Implementation, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 309)
    - Minutes and Communication, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 310)
    - Chronological Record of Task Force Activities, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 311)
    - Response of Men's and Women's Depts. to Task Force Report of January 17, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 312)
    - Conference with Harold Lewis, January 22, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 313)
    - Student Response to Final Task Force Report, January 1975-February 1975 (Box 5, Folder 314)
    - Curriculum Committee Meeting regarding Task Force Report, February 7, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 315)
    - UFCAS Action regarding Task Force Report, Spring 1975 (Box 5, Folder 316)
    - Report of committee on athletics to UFCAS, October 1975 (Box 5, Folder 317)
  - Women's Athletics
    - AIAW
      - 1st Delegate Assembly, November 1973 (Box 5, Folder 318)
      - Resolutions on Scholarships, August 1974 (Box 5, Folder 319)
      - Code of Ethics, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 320)
      - Correspondence from AIAW President to Voting Members, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 321)
      - Correspondence with Kenneth Pye regarding Title IX, October 1976 (Box 5, Folder 322)
    - NCAA
      - NCAA Plan for Women's Athletics, April 1975 (Box 5, Folder 323)
      - AIAW's Response to the NCAA Plan, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 324)
      - AAHPER's Response to the NCAA Plan, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 325)
    - Title IX
      - Opportunity Knocks through Title IX, editorial in Update, April 1974 (Box 5, Folder 326)
      - Gwen Gregory on Title IX - notes from her speech, April 1974 (Box 5, Folder 327)
      - Speech by Dr. Katherine Ley at SDAAHPER, Spring 1974 (Box 5, Folder 328)
      - Final Text, July 21, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 329)
    - At Duke
      - Growth of Women's Athletics, 1971-1975 (Box 5, Folder 330)
      - Formation of the Duke Chapter of AIAW, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 331)
      - Summary of Women's Athletics, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 332)
      - Position Paper on Women's Athletics, September 27, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 333)
      - Summary of Women's Athletics, 1976 (Written by the Men's P. E. Dept.) (Box 5, Folder 334)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series consists of three scrapbooks of clippings, photographs, programs, correspondence and other materials related to the Women's Department of Health and Physical Education. There is some description of each scrapbook's contents below; there are more detailed inventories in the University Archives.
  Please note that the scrapbooks are fragile and must be handled carefully.
  - 1932-1941 (Box 6)
    This scrapbook is a collection of newspaper clippings and photographs of events related to the women's physical education department. The items are arranged chronologically.
  - 1958-1973 (Box 7)
    This scrapbook is chronologically arranged by school year. Each school year begins with a list of teaching staff. The scrapbook also includes programs from athletic and recreational events; articles and programs on various conferences; travel itineraries from staff members' trips; wedding announcements from major students; Christmas letters sent to retired staff and majors; notes from majors; articles related to Duke women's physical education and the Woman's College, as well as events at Duke; and brochures on the Women's Recreation Association and majoring in physical education. The scrapbook includes some photographs of events, teams, faculty, and majors.
  - 1973-1976 (Box 6)
    This scrapbook is a collection of newspaper clippings, programs, brochures, posters, Christmas letters, and schedules. The items are arranged chronologically.